Okay, so we've got indigenous Americans,
enslaved Africans, and Europeans all
mixed together in the Americas like a
stanky colonial stew. And I bet you're
here to learn about how those
interactions affected or changed the
perspectives of all those involved. If
that's true, then I hope you're ready to
get them brain cows milked because I
stand at the ready to milk them. Let's
get to it. Okay, so if you've been
paying attention for the last few
videos, then it's not going to come as
any surprise to hear that as the Spanish
concistadored all over indigenous
America, folks on both sides noticed
that they were pretty different from
each other. or to deploy the lexicon of
our AP overlords. As contact between the
Europeans and the various indigenous
peoples of the Americas increased, they
asserted divergent worldviews. Now, what
in the fresh heck does that mean? Well,
a worldview describes a people's
constellation of cultural experiences,
like their history and their belief
systems and their language, etc. And all
of that combined dictates how they make
sense out of the world. For example, if
you were born and raised here in the
United States, then you likely believe
that democracy is the best form of
government. And let's not be too modest
that every country on earth should also
be a democracy. That's just part of the
American worldview that lives all the
way down in our guts, which is to say at
the level of assumption. And if someone
came along and disagreed with us and
they said, for example, you know, like h
I think communism is a better way to go.
Well, then that dear interlocutor better
hold on to his butt because we're about
to sick a flock of bald eagles on that
man's hind parts.
Okay, I'm now getting word that this
video will in fact be on the internet
and that I'm obliged to tell you that I
am not a communist and that I love
democracy. My PR department apparently
ran the numbers and it turned out there
was an 84% chance that internet people
would assume that I was persuading the
delicate brain folds of America's youth
to quote go full comm. So statement made
disaster avert. Anyway, the whole point
of me giving you this example is to show
that world views are deeply embedded and
for the undicern they just assume that
their worldview is the best way to
understand the world. And when those
people encounter other people with a
whole different set of assumptions for
how the world should work, the instinct
tends to be they're my enemy. And we
happen to have a fun word for that
reality, namely ethnosentris. Anyway,
now that you understand that whole mess,
let's compare the world views of the
Europeans and the indigenous peoples
with whom they interact. First, they had
differing worldviews regarding land use.
Europeans believed that land could be
owned by individuals, but the dominant
indigenous belief was that land
contained spiritual qualities that bound
all things together and thus belonged to
all people communally. And so when the
Europeans showed up, they looked at the
way the indigenous people were handling
their land and they were like, "No, I
ain't doing this right. We'll show you
how." Second, they held differing
worldviews concerning belief systems or
if you're sassy, religion. Now,
Europeans were on the whole Christian
and adhere to a complex set of dogmas
and doctrines, most notably the doctrine
of a single god. And although indigenous
belief systems varied, many of them
believed in multiple gods and did not
separate the spiritual material realms
as was common in European Christianity.
Third, in terms of gender roles,
Europeans tended to be patriarchal,
where men have the power, whereas
indigenous people tended to be more
egalitarian, which is to say equal, even
to the extent that some family and power
structures were matrinal, meaning they
passed through the mother's descendants.
And finally, in terms of family
structure, Europeans tended to emphasize
the nuclear family as normative, whereas
indigenous peoples lived together in
extended families containing multiple
generations. So, you can begin to see
why the Spanish instinct toward
indigenous groups was to patronize and
subjugate them. They both held different
world views and that felt like a threat.
Now everything I just said is true. Most
of the early years of contact between
Europeans and the indigenous groups were
full of misunderstandings. But
eventually in some cases, Europeans and
Native Americans adopted some useful
aspects of each other's culture. For
example, due to the Spanish effort to
establish Christian missions in
southwest North America, many indigenous
peoples converted to Christianity or at
least adopted some useful aspects of
Christianity. Now, certainly arguable
that these conversions occurred due to
the heavy-handed and sometimes brutal
tactics of the Spanish missionaries.
Hey, you know how we just killed a bunch
of y'all? Well, we just wanted to follow
up on that and say that Jesus loves you
and has a wonderful plan for your life.
Who wants to pray? But, you know, being
polytheist, indigenous people saw no
conflict in adding the Christian God to
the worship of other gods. And it might
have been enticing for them to convert
when they observed that the Spanish
remained largely unaffected by the
epidemics killing large portion of the
indigenous population. But the problem
showed up when those indigenous people
who had converted to Christianity did
not practice the faith in the way that
satisfied the Spanish priest. In other
words, according to the priest, these
savages in front of them didn't seem to
understand that Jesus would not abide
any other gods to sit at the heavenly
table with him. In fact, in the Spanish
mind, what the primitive people could
not understand was that Jesus wasn't the
god just of the Europeans, but the god
of the whole dang universe. And whatever
gods the indigenous people worshiped
were no gods at all and should be tossed
on the metaphysical garbage. But even
so, it turns out that some indigenous
people who accepted Christianity also
adapted it to their own worldview, which
is what we call synretatism. For
example, in the 16th century, a man of
Aztec lineage began receiving
visitations from the Virgin Mary, who's
a central feature of Catholic
Christianity. And in these visions, she
instructed him to build a church in her
honor on the side of a torn down Aztec
temple. And she became known as the
Virgin of Guadalupe. And notice that she
is portrayed with brown skin, which is
clearly not a choice made by the
Spanish. Additionally, because
indigenous belief systems in the area
emphasized a mother goddess and a cult
of fertility, many embraced her as
worthy of veneration. So, out of this
encounter with Christianity and
indigenous belief systems, a blending
occurred in which the indigenous people
developed a form of Christianity that
reflected their own worldview. On the
other side, European settlers adopted
many useful aspects of indigenous
culture. For example, the English
settlers in North America just about
died before the natives of the region
taught them local agricultural
techniques. and French settlers, mostly
interested in the robust American fur
trade, often intermarried with
indigenous women in order to firm up
trade relations. But here's where I tell
you that the mutuality between the two
groups was for sure overshadowed by the
tensions created by their encounter. You
see, as European colonists continue to
claim land for themselves and therefore
challenge native sovereignty, conflicts
occurred between the two groups. And
those conflicts typically led to one of
two outcomes. First, tensions could be
settled through diplomacy. And I
mentioned this earlier, but in some
cases, Native Americans defended
themselves from Europeans by allying
with them against other native groups.
This occurred when several groups under
Aztec power allied with the Spanish in
order to topple their oppressors. But
then the second outcome was violence
through military resistance. And the
best example I know of in this period is
the Tino Rebellion. So in 1511, the
native people of modern day Puerto Rico
rebelled against the Spanish intrusion.
As it turned out, they had grown real
tired of the brutal conditions of the
Encomienda system and the threat to
their cultural traditions as the Spanish
attempted to convert them to
Christianity. And so they decided to
drive out the Spanish with force. Now,
because the Tina were more numerous than
the Spanish, they had some success at
the beginning. But over time, the
superior weaponry of the Spanish won the
day and they suppressed the rebellion.
And that whole event confused the
Spanish because like weren't these
people savages? And shouldn't they be
grateful that we're bringing the glories
of Western civilization to them? Well,
apparently the Tino did not agree with
that assessment. And so they tried to
whip some Spanish butt. And that gets me
thinking about the last section of this
video. Namely, you need to know that as
these groups encountered each other,
their interaction sparked a debate back
in Spain. And you know, I suppose to
their credit as news of the brutality of
the encoma system and African slavery
reached Spain, they were like, "Is this
okay?" And that question with respect to
indigenous people sparked what's known
as the viodal debates in Spain. On one
side was Barthole Deascus, who was once
himself a concistador in the Americas.
Upon his arrival there, he owned land
and indigenous slaves as an encomando
and even fought in a war against
indigenous groups. However, over time,
he changed his mind and became one of
their chief advocates in Spain. He
argued that indigenous people were fully
human and thus ought not to be subject
to the inhumane ravages of systems like
Incomienda. Now, to be fair, Lascasa
still held a very paternalistic view of
indigenous peoples. And what I mean is
he advocated for them, but he still saw
them as univilized compared to the
Spanish and were therefore in need of
European uh, you know, toutelage. But
then on the other side of the debate was
Juan Guin de Seepda who argued that
indigenous people were in fact less than
human and therefore the subjugation and
brutality actually helped them along the
way into their full humanity. Not
surprisingly Sephveda's view won the day
and that helped the Spanish to justify
their harsh treatment of the indigenous
peoples with whom they interacted. But
then a similar prick of conscience hit
the Europeans regarding their growing
dependence on African slavery and all
the brutality and horror that
characterized that institution. But not
to worry, the Bible scholars showed up
and Pope explained it real nice for
everybody. They pointed to an episode in
the book of Genesis known as the curse
of Ham. Now, Ham was one of the sons of
Noah of Ark fame. And long story short,
Noah went ahead and cursed Ham and said
that he and his descendants will be
servants all their days. And the Bible
scholar said, "Look, Africans are the
descendants of Ham, so we're justified
in enslaving them. God says so." To
which somebody in the back of the room
responded, "Uh, where does it say that
Ham's descendants were African?" To
which the scholar said, "Hey, shut up."
And this kind of argument became even
more common as Europeans interacted with
more and more Africans. And by the 16th
century, they had developed a concrete
concept of race and racial difference
and combined that with all their
religious arguments. And all that put
together, boom, novel justifications for
the brutal treatment of other races.
Okay, you can click here to get my A
pushheimler review guide, which is the
fastest way to study for your exams. And
you can click here to watch my other
videos from unit one. I'll catch you on
the flip-flop. I'm Lar.